<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter>
  <title>Focus</title>
  <para><emphasis role="italic">A Whiff of Steam</emphasis> is a 2D role-playing game settled in steam-punk world. The magic is fully fused with the technology. Technology is explained in terms of magic and considered as one of the fields of magical studies.</para>
  <para>The view in the game will be divided in two groups - separate detailed tactical view for fights, and consistent view using trimetric projection for travel and location exploration, as seen in Fallout 1 and 2 or Sim City 4. Main locations, like cities, dungeons, quest related places will be created by artists and the rest of the world, i.e. wilderness, is going to be automatically generated, because of size of the world. The general stylistics of game will be eastern ﬂavoured realistic comics style, slightly taking from Chinese Manhua comics tradition. Dreams will be visualised as comic stripes.</para>
  <para>Hero has access to every part of a game world and can travel freely. But it doesn&apos;t mean that he has to walk everywhere. He will be able to choose between using public means of transport, like trains, traveling on foot between artists&apos; created locations or using fast travel option. Fast travel option is available only by using road signs, showing directions between locations connected by roads. Fast traveling is risky, hero and/or his team can randomly encounter hostile creatures. Also not all locations are accessible in fast travel mode, the country is not urbanised enough to get everywhere by train. The protagonist must travel on foot to reach some essential parts or hidden, secluded places. This, in conjunction with size of the world, will encourage player to explore.</para>
  <para>Another important feature of <emphasis role="italic">A Whiff of Steam</emphasis> are interactions with NPCs. Hero will have a chance to build a complex interpersonal relationships, while it won&apos;t be easy. He will have to prove being reliable first. The way the hero dresses will have an impact on people&apos;s reactions. They will be more eager to share their thoughts and troubles with wealthy mysterious stranger than the poor one. Generosity also affects their attitude. Protagonist&apos;s lies, while discovered, change the trust people have in him. Hero may team up with someone to complete the task, but it won&apos;t mean that that person will follow him, everywhere he goes. In the game world people have their own lives as well and they won&apos;t sacrifice everything so easily. Unless he proofs them being somehow useful, they won&apos;t support him. Creating such huge number of various personalities wouldn&apos;t be possible, unless minor characters will have generated personalities. For generating personalities we will use personality archetypes, zodiac stereotypes and enneagram, for short time attitude and feelings, we will use biorhythms.</para>
  <para>Game&apos;s story is built around mysterious events. Protagonist awakes near the crashed train, he&apos;s severe wounded and can&apos;t move but notices that someone is trying to rob him. Soon he looses consciousness again and wakes up in hospital with amnesia. He is tormented with bad dreams. The only hint about his past he has is a note with name and phone number in his pocket. Nobody recognises him, it seems that he has never been to this part of the country. Soon he starts looking for his own past, uncovering his criminal deeds conflicting with his good subconscious side. His dreams become longer and more clear - seems that he was the one who caused the train crash. Police starts to investigate the case and ﬁnds that he was involved in it, while he still cannot remember anything except for causing the crash. The truth won&apos;t be easy to discover.</para>
  <para>The country, where action takes place, lays on large island and is isolated from rest of the world. It is governed by Community of the Faithful, church led by orthodox mages. The government is afraid that the world&apos;s order is about to change, and carefully watches every revolutionary move. For many years technology, commonly considered as equal to magical science, has been inferior to magic, in fact. But some people fascinated by the power of technology tried to separate those two fields of science. Governors are afraid that technology can eventually became more popular than magic, and people will no longer accept the control and authority of Community of the Faithful. Special services invigilate citizens and report suspicious activities. Single citizen is not aware of the scale of invigilation until he or she is being watched and loses control over his or her life.</para>
  <para>The hero&apos;s story, although important to him, doesn&apos;t play a big role in the world order, it is just a part of larger picture. It&apos;s going to have an influence on the behaviour of the people struggling with their own concerns but not on the large-scale world events themselves.</para>
  <para><emphasis role="italic">A Whiff of Steam</emphasis> will strongly affect on players&apos; emotions. Story totally supports emotions that we want to show - rejection, surprise, yet still some hope. The protagonist will be cast out of the society and scared to discover his own past, the past of cruel and heartless man.</para>
  <para>Fights will not be key feature of the game, but will be present. They keep the whole game world more realistic and well balanced. They also provide optional things to do while traveling. There will be used timed turn based system and action points, that can be spend on movement or other actions. Fights as non key element of gameplay will be optional. Player will be able to choose in menu if he wants to enable &quot;automatic conflict resolution&quot;, that will make whole fight led by AI.</para>
  <para>Most skills will evolve by training, the more player use certain skills the better they will get. But there will be more skills than those related to fights, there will be also plenty of practical skills, and what’s new, social skills. All built to same level of complexity.</para>
  <figure>
    <title>Stylistics concept</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../artwork/concept1.png" width="12cm"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
</chapter>
