<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter>
  <title>Story outline</title>
  <para>The hero, Cornelius King, is a double agent. Community of the Faithful, or to be more precise one of them, mage called Oren Worthington, placed him into the pro technical underground after few of the prestigious mages died in suspicious circumstances. King&apos;s work proved that there are terrorists cells inside protech underground. He was placed in one of them. And then the troubles for him begins. He got emotionally involved with the leader of his cell Lutricia McNeal. Little did he knew that Worthington had foreseen that something like this happened. All the time King was working for him - he was carefully watched by another agent, whose only mission was to control King&apos;s actions. Magician carefully choose a person to do that. It was Kings cousin: Eleanor &quot;Ellen&quot; Montgomery. It was Ellen who put King into the crushed train. And she was the person he saw &quot;trying to rob him&quot;. In fact Ellen had to report about King&apos;s relation with McNeal to the Community of the Faithful. But she would not want her cousin’s death. So she started her own game.</para>
  <para>When Ellen discovered that in the train there will be traveling Worthington&apos;s daughter Devon, a very talented young magician, she made sure that the underground will get to know about it. And that McNeal&apos;s cell will be involved into the ambush. Her plan was McNeal to die into the crash. And King&apos;s memories about her to be wiped out with powerful spell. The second part of the plan went perfect. Cornelius was hit by the spell. The entire terrorist cell die in the trap (killed by people hired by Ellen - who was assigned to this mission by Wortington) except McNeal. She was not there by mysterious reasons. Ellen was furious cause she was for her the most important person to eliminate. She wanted to erase his cousin memory and kill her underground lover - to make sure Cornelius to stay alive. When McNeal didn&apos;t show at the scene of a terrorist attack Ellen decided to change her plan. And leave his cousin outside as a bait in outside world for McNeal to find.</para>
  <para>Mages made sure that King&apos;s wounds will look as he was in the train during the crash. They left him with a card with the name: Lutricia McNeal and the phone number in one of terrorist&apos;s flat. Hoping that he will find McNeal and they would be able to catch and question her.</para>
</chapter>
